Alessandro Di Candia

Seasoned tech leader passionate about customer experience and engagement.

alex@enjine.net 646.541.1192 Ferndale, PA 18921 https://dicandia.tech

A customer as anyone to whom I am delivering value. To serve my customers well, I listen carefully and work for the good of the group. These principles are evident in all aspects of my work, from leadership to shipping code. Over the past 20 years I have worked in many industries with many people, using many technologies; as such, my accrued technical, analytical, and communication skills position me as the catalyst from concept to execution. I enjoy solving challenging problems and creating processes that elevate productivity, quality, and happiness.

Professional Experience

VP Technology, Digital Platform

Group1001 / Gainbridge

2017 - 2020

Remote to NY/MA/IN

VP of Tech for an internally-funded startup launching a direct-to-consumer annuity platform. Responsible for technology strategy, decisioning and leadership. Supported growth from \$0/week to \$1MM+/week in sales in under 12 months. Reporting to CXO, coordinated delivery across multiple agency and internal teams. Collaborated directly with Executives, Product, Marketing, Customer Service, Compliance, and domain experts to deliver solutions aligned with the strategic vision. Introduced domain-driven-design (DDD) as a method of improving cross-functional communication, estimation accuracy, and product quality.

Accomplishments

- Hired and retained a distributed team of 10 engineers; effectively managing 50% of the company's staff.
- Established career growth paths for engineering team members, organized team off-sites and arranged for attendance at conferences.
- Established processes for handling incident and change management, internal audit, and customer service.
- Implemented monitoring and telemetry to measure and inform establishment of KPI's and baselines for customer- and system-facing SLAs.
- 10% net reduction of production bugs release-over-release by implementing formalized QA processes during sprints and releases.
- 25-30% increase in velocity by introducing domain-driven design.
- Decreased open bugs by 50% within 6 months.
- Reduced technical debt by 30% by commissioning an architecture redesign and deploying it in parallel, gradually sunsetting problematic services.
- Delivered a 30% savings in AWS costs.

Principal Engineer

Synacor, Inc. (SYNC)

2014 – 2017

Remote to Buffalo, NY

Looking to expand my experience into more corporate/enterprise environments, I took a contract with Synacor as a Frontend Engineer on a fully distributed team. Technical contributions were predominantly full-stack front-end on top of a SOA backend, full CI pipeline and a formal change

management process across all engineering teams. Shortly before my contract was up, I was asked to join as an FTE and take on the responsibilities of Tech Lead. I agreed, and shortly thereafter was being asked to fulfill additional roles as needed. I consulted across teams when technical expertise, rapid prototyping, or domain knowledge was needed and acted as interim Engineering Manager in absence of the role being filled. During my time here I was able to continue my passion for frontend work and creating great user experiences, but I was also given the opportunity to exercise my leadership skills in a formal management role.

Accomplishments

- 10% increase in velocity across all company UI teams using a UI component library I coauthored.
- Reduced time to first commit during onboarding by 40% by creating scripts and documentation for new employees and contractors.
- Increased my team's capacity by mentoring teammates who were not UI Engineers; teaching them the key skills and concepts needed to work with the codebase.
- Increased code-quality within my team by establishing coding standards and strictly enforcing them during code reviews.

Founder

Bitwise Web Services, L.LC.

2009 - 2014

Remote

Having learned much of what it takes to be successful in professional services during my first 9 years of employment, I started my own consulting company where I succeeded (and failed) by my own accord - using each experience as an opportunity for growth. I performed CTO/Technical cofounder duties for several startups while also architecting and coding the applications from scratch and managing offshore teams of mobile developers. I was also hired into several agencies to contribute extra engineering capacity and train their teams to use new technologies, coding bestpractices and delivery workflows. Even after my contracts had ended, I remained in touch with several clients, hearing much positive feedback about the residual effects of our engagement.

Accomplishments

- Fulfilled all roles for business operations: sales, marketing, client relations, project management, engineering, and accounting.
- Successfully procured and retained a roster of clients for multiple long-term contracts.
- Partnered with design firms to create brands for SMB's; developed SEO and search campaigns matched to the positioning strategy.
- Planned, estimated, and executed various custom software solutions in both public and private sectors spanning music, education, health, government, food, and records archiving.
- Demonstrated year-over-year growth between 5% and 7%.

Director, Product Engineering Ultrastar / LiveNation

2000 - 2009 NYC/Brooklyn

After undergrad, I began work as webmaster at a startup founded by David Bowie. Part ISP, part subscription-fanclub/advance-ticketing platform. Early on, I was called upon to interact directly with fans as well as artists/clients. Clients included David himself, The Rolling Stones, The Who,

Madonna, Mariah Carey, The Police, AC/DC and many others. My solid handling of those responsibilities allowed me to rapidly evolve into more of a player/coach as the team grew to 5+ designers and developers. I was responsible for ensuring our team delivered all client work as well as prototyping and pitching new features to prospective clients. Out of necessity, I invented my own processes, workflows and libraries to organize work, set expectations with client managers, and provide engineers a high level of reusability and extensibility between projects. I also organized and executed exclusive members-only experiences and live webcasts from venues.

Accomplishments

- Reduced agency and contractor costs by 70% by singlehandedly taking ownership of entire codebase.
- Reduced delivery time by 50% by normalizing development and deployment processes.
- Directly affected new client acquisition by prototyping new products and features.
- Directed design and development teams in delivery of client work.
- Accelerated the hiring process 4x by creating a questionnaire and battery of tests and for technical screenings and interviews.
- Achieved higher operational excellence by assisting client managers in setting expectations and providing teams a normalized framework within which to operate.
- Increased employee happiness by organizing weekly team-building events.

Core Competencies		
Executive	Product + User Experience	Technical
People Management	Brand + Marketing Strategy	Technical Product Ownership
Conflict Resolution	Product Development	Frontend Development
Talent Acquisition	IA / UI / UX	API Development
Strategic Planning + Tradeoffs	Analytics + A/B Testing	Solutions Architecture
Business Analysis	Performance Analysis	Security + Compliance
	_	·

Core Technical Skills

Languages: JavaScript (ES2018/React/Node), HTML5, CSS3, PHP, Java

Tools: git, Webpack, Parcel, LESS, SCSS, Ansible, Terraform

Ops/Infra: Docker, Kubernetes, Jenkins, Bamboo, TeamCity, OpsGenie, AWS, GCP **Productivity**: Adobe CS, Sketch, Miro, Atlassian, Slack, Zoom, Tuple, MS Office/G Suite

Education

- B.A. Advertising/Communications, Penn State University
- 3.8 GPA, Dean's List 6 of 8 semesters
- Minors in Business Management, Italian
- Work/study as Webmaster for College of Communications